<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[A sermon preached at Hitchin in ...] 1587. the 17.day of Nouember [...]</title>
            <author>Harris, Edward, fl. 1587-1590.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1590</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 79 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 42 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A02672</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 12804</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S112492</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99847741</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99847741</idno>
            <idno type="VID">12801</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A02672)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 12801)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 464:06)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>[A sermon preached at Hitchin in ...] 1587. the 17.day of Nouember [...]</title>
                  <author>Harris, Edward, fl. 1587-1590.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 79 [i.e. 74] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By [W. Kearney? for] Iohn Morris &amp; I. B[owen] dwelling in S. Iohns ..,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Printed at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1590.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Title in part from STC as title page as filmed too dark to read. Printer's name suggested by STC.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect; title page as filmed too dark to read.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  16th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:12801:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:12801:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:12801:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:12801:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:12801:3"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:12801:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A SERMON PREACHED AT HITCHIN IN THE yeare of our Lord, 1587 the 17, day of November, being the firſt day of the 29 yeare of the Queenes Maieſties reigne.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>By Edward Harris, Maſter of Arts and Preacher of this word of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Printed at London by Iohn Morris &amp; I.B. dwelling in S. Iohns ſtreete. 1590.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:12801:4"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:12801:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>TO THE FAITHFVLL AND BELOVED IN THE Lord his brethren knowne to him in Hertford-ſhire, grace and peace in Chriſt Ieſu.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Here are novv three yeeres paſſed ſince at the request of ſome I communicated this ſermon of mine in vvriting to thoſe vvhich not long after obtained for it allovvance to go abroad in print, and novv at the last, it having receiued the fruite of that allovvance, I offer it vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to as many of you as deſire to profite by the remembrance of that vvhich yee once heard before. Vſe it (I beſeech you) to that end for vvhich I first ſpake it and novv offer it vnto you, that is, to your further building vp in the feare of our God, and honour of our Soueraigne. If you remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber
<pb facs="tcp:12801:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>any more than is here ſet dovvne, vſe that alſo to the ſame end; and laying a part all vanities of the vvorld, ſet your minds on thoſe things vvhich may profite in the day of the viſitation of all fleſh. The grace of our God be vvith you.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>From my chamber at</hi> North Mimmes, <hi>this 16, of October, 1590.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>E. H.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:12801:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>Feare God, Honor the King. <bibl>
                  <hi>I.</hi> Peter. <hi>2.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE ſweete ſhowers which fel in the forenoone (deere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly beloued in Chriſt Ieſu) might, if the ground of your hearts be not braſſe or adamant, not only cauſe the ſeed of the word which ye haue ſo often receiued, to bring forth in you the herbe of an holy pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion, and fruite of an holy life, but moreouer &amp; beſides that, might make way to the better planting of any other good and godly inſtruction in your minds, I doubt not, but ye keepe in remembrance the ſumme of that which hath bene taught; namely, both who is the author of your deliuerance from all your enimies, to wit, not the arme of fleſh, but God himſelfe, and alſo by what meanes he hath brought this to paſſe; to wit, by the godly and Chriſtian gouernment of our gracious ſoueraigne, the annointed meſſenger
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:12801:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>of the Lord in this behalfe: and as I doubt not, but yee remember theſe things, ſo I charitablie perſwade my ſelfe, that yee make enquirie and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mande of your owne ſoules, by what dueties towards God the author, and by what reuerence toward the Prince the inſtrument of this our common ſafetie and welfare, ye may ſhew your ſelues thankfull receiuers of ſo great a benefite. Harken therefore what the ſpirite of God which is in him, and onely knoweth the minde and will of God, requireth of you by the mouth of ſaint Peter. For his owne ſelfe, he ſeeketh no more at your hands, but that yee feare him: For the perſon of his annointed, he exacteth nothing elſe but that ye honour her. For ſo ſaith the holy Apoſtle, 1. Epiſt. Chap. 2. <hi>Feare God</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>and Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor the king.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For the firſt of theſe two, it is no new commandement, but an ancient and old precept renewed, as being a matter of chriſtian obedience requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:12801:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>in both Teſtaments. Moſes the lawgiuer of Iſrael, Leuit. 19. 14. ſaith to the inheritance of the Lord the children which came out of th loynes of Iacob, <hi>Thouſhalt feare</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>the Lord thy God.</hi> Againe, Leuit. 25. 17. he ſaith, <hi>Let euerie one feare his God.</hi> Like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, Deuter. 20. he chargeth them, ſaying, <hi>Follow the Lord your God, and feare ye him.</hi> Our Sauiour Chriſt, Luk. 12. teacheth men to feare him, who after he hath killed the bodie, can caſt the ſoule into hell fire, that is, God, And beſides this place of ſaint Peter, ſaint Iohn alſo, Reuelations the fourteenth and the ſeuenth, hauing ſeene and Angell flying thorough the midſt of heauen, which had an euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting Goſpel to preach vnto them that dwell on the earth, euen to euery nation and kinred, and tongue, and people, teſtifieth howe this Angel cried with a lowd voice, ſaying, <hi>Feare God, and giue glorie to him.</hi> Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, ſith wee are compaſſed with ſuch a cloud of moſt glorious and
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:12801:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>faithfull witneſſes, make your recko<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning how ye heare not me, but Moſes, Chriſt, Peter, Iohn, and the Angels of heauen crying vnto you, <hi>Feare God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Some will ſay peraduenture, all this needeth not, there is none here (we hope) but feare God truely. Well bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, to <hi>the lavv and to the testimonie,</hi> let that be our iudge, &amp; our owne con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences witneſſes, whether the true feare of God which is here comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by the holy ghoſt, be in the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt part of men now adayes.</p>
            <p>To know then, whether we be en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dewed with this true and earneſt feare of God or no, there are among other, three eſpeciall wayes whereby ye ſhal certainly know the ſame.</p>
            <p>The firſt way is, the birth of it: For if the feare of God that is in you, come out of that ſpring, and be bred in that ſort as true feare is, then haue you cauſe to reioice.</p>
            <p>The ſecond is, by the naturall and liuely effectes of the ſame feare: For doubtleſſe euerie thing, eſpecially the
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:12801:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>motions of Gods ſpirite, working not counterfaitly but according to it owne nature, it muſt needs be a falſe and ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtardly feare of God, which vttereth not it ſelfe in conuenient meaſure by the proper effects of true feare.</p>
            <p>The third way is, by ſuch things as vnſeparably follow and accompanie the true feare of God, which S. Peter ſpeaketh of.</p>
            <p>For the firſt way, yee muſt obſerue &amp; know, that the earneſt feare of God ſpringeth and proceedeth of a right and reuerend knowledge, and medita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the ſurpaſſing power, bottom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe wiſe dome, infallible prouidence, vndefiled iuſtice, incomparable good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, and other ſuch heauenly attributes of Gods nature, as the ſcripture giueth vnto it. For when the conſideration of mans mind is truely fixed and ſet vpon the inward view &amp; beholding of theſe things, the glorie of them is ſuch, that it doth ſtrike &amp; poſſeſſe the heart with an vnfained reuerence of that perſon, who is of ſuch a nature, as by ſo glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:12801:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>names employing ſo great and wonderfull effects, is rather pointed at than fullie defined. This that I ſay, is manifeſt by the tenth chapter of the Prophet Ieremie. For conſidering how none was like to the Lord in power; how he was great, and incomparablie wiſer then all the prudent men of the nations, and how none was like to him in all the kingdomes of the world: to ſhew what this meditation bredde in him, and what it worketh in all the children of God, he burſteth forth in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to theſe words, <hi>Who ſhall not feare thee O king of nations?</hi> As if he ſhould ſay, that whoſoeuer did rightly meditate and ſtudie vpon theſe things, could not but hereby grow into a true feare of God, or at the leaſt, that the vnfai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned and true feare of God ſpringeth hereupon. Prouided alwayes, that we take this view by the word of God onely, and not by the fancie or ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gination of mans braine. Here is then the firſt point whereby yee may know whether yee feare God truely (as ſaint
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:12801:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>Peter commandeth.) Haue ye exerci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed your wits in this meditation? haue yee taken a diligent view of theſe things out of the moſt faithfull aſſerti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and examples of the word of God? and hath that feare of God which is in you, proceeded and riſen hereof? then is there hope, that the feare of God in you is not counterfait. But now (my brethren) if the moſt men be vtterly ignorant of theſe points, &amp; in a manner all men remiſſe, negli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent, and cold in taking ſuch view of the nature of God, how may we not iuſtly feare, that the moſt men now a dayes are vtterly deſtitute of this grace and gift of the true feare of God?</p>
            <p n="2">2 The ſecond meanes, whereby yee may know and diſcerne whether your hearts be poſſeſſed with a true feare of the Almightie, is by the ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects, which are diuerſe, the chiefe and principall whereof are theſe that fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low.</p>
            <p>Firſt, the true feare of God is of ſuch
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:12801:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>force and working, that it maketh him in whom it is, to hate and decline that which is euill and vngodly in the ſight of the Lord, I ſay not, how they which haue this feare do not ſinne at all; but that the faithfull are by this feare, as by a moſt fit inſtrume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of the holy ghoſt, kept backe from following the luſts of vngodlineſſe, and haue ſuch a watch<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>word giuen them continually in their hearts, that they are not eaſily drawne to any notorious breach and tranſgreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of Gods commandements. This effect of this true feare of God is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by Abraham the father of the faith full, Gen. 20. For when Abimelech the king of Gerar, who had taken a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way his wife, being brought to the knowledge of his iniquitie, demanded of Abraham what he ſaw in the land, that he manifeſted not that ſhe was his wife: Abraham anſwered, ſaying; <hi>I thought</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>ſurely the feare of God is not in this plase, therefore they vvill ſlay me for my vvines ſake:</hi> As if he had ſaid, how there was no hope in
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:12801:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>him that he ſhould finde any honeſt dealing there, where the vnfained and true feare of God was wanting. To this agreeth a moſt notable example which we finde written, Exod. 1. 17. where it is ſhewed, how that when Pharao had commanded-the mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wines to make away the men children of the Iſraelites, that which reſtrained them from committing ſo horrible a fact, was the true feare of God which they had before their eyes: for ſo Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes teſtifieth of them, ſaying, <hi>But the midvvines feared God, and did not accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the commandement of the king, but ſaued the men children.</hi> Yea Salomon maketh it a generall rule, that <hi>the feare of God cauſeth a man not onely to decline euill, Pron.</hi> 13. but more ouer <hi>to hate the euill, Pron.</hi> 8. 13. And for the more plaineneſſe, he maketh mention of foure points of iniquitie which cannot dwell with the feare of God: to wit, arrogancie, pride, the euill way, and a double tongue; and ſheweth by ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample in himſelfe, how if a man haue
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:12801:10" rendition="simple:additions"/>the vpright feare of God abiding and working in him, he will auoid and ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hor theſe enormities. The firſt <hi>enormity</hi> is arrogancie, which is, <hi>Alying perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion and boasting, that one hath thoſe graces and that abilitie which he hath not:</hi> and this iniquitie raigneth in the greateſt part of men. Yee that are of the miniſterie, looke into them of our owne calling: There are infinite in a manner, which being vnable for want of gifts to fulfill any the leaſt part of the miniſters office and charge truely, notwithſtanding preſume and booſt themſelues to be ſufficient men for that calling when it is nothing ſo, and hereupon breake in and come within the liſtes of the holy mount of God, &amp; thruſt themſelues into the ſanctua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie of the moſt holy one. Theſe are monſtrouſly arrogant, and therefore out of all queſtion deſtitute of the true feare of the Lord. Of this ſort are ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny profeſſors now adayes, which ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing not as yet profited ſo farre as that they know the <hi>word of the beginning</hi>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:12801:10" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <hi>of Chriſt Ieſu,</hi> or firſt principles of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, yet boaſt themſelues to be rich in the knowledge of God &amp; of Chriſt Ieſu. Of the ſame ſtampe generally are Papiſts, who arro gating to themſelues by nature freewil to forſake cuill &amp; to do good, which they haue not power to merit heauen by their works which all men lacke, ſhew the true feare of God not to be in them.</p>
            <p>The ſecond <hi>enormitie</hi> is <hi>Pride,</hi> which is, <hi>achalenging of glorie, praiſe, and dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie to ones ſelfe, in respect of thoſe graces and giftes which are in him.</hi> They that are carried away with this vngodly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, they are alſo void of the true feare of God. Such are in the miniſtrie thoſe now a dayes, who knowing themſelues to haue thoſe good graces and giftes which their betters in eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſticall place and calling do want, thinke much that their place is none higher, their liuings no larger, their eſtimation no greater, and thereupon make it their chiefe ſtudie, how they may come and attaine to better pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>motion.
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:12801:11" rendition="simple:additions"/>Such are among the gentrie thoſe, that for the abundance of their outward bleſſings cannot content thè<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, vnleſſe they may haue ſome higher title than whereby they are yet called. Briefely, ſuch are all thoſe, who of a glory that they haue in their owne gifts, aſpire to an higher place in the common welth, after the manner of Abſhalom, or hunt after and ſtriue for the preheminence in the church, after the manner of Diotrephes: for thus to do is <hi>pride,</hi> which ſinne cannot raigne in any perſon, and the man feare God aright too.</p>
            <p>The third <hi>enormitie</hi> abhorred of ſuch as feare God truelie, is <hi>the euil may,</hi> that is to ſay, all courſe and trade of life and liuing, which ſauoureth of vngod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe: as liuing by vſurie, coſinage, theeuerie, extortion, leading of ones life in filthineſſe, adulterie, wanton<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, idleneſſe, or any other crime, that the church of God is offended withall. This courſe whoſoeuer taketh (as the world is full of ſuch now
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:12801:11" rendition="simple:additions"/>adaies) they can by no coulourable meanes be ſhewed to fear God aright, whatſoeuer they outwardly pretend.</p>
            <p>The fourth <hi>enormitie</hi> which cannot ſtand nor dwell togither with the true feare of God, is <hi>adouble tongue:</hi> with which ſinne there are ſpecially two kinds of people infected: one is of thè, who will ſpeake as faire as Angels to a mans face, but will ſtraight way, or whenſoeuer occaſion is miniſtred, ſlan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der them moſt beaſtly behind their backes: Another ſort is of them, who in the company of ſuch as profeſſe the truth ſincerely will make a great ſhew of godlineſſe, but when they come in companie of others which are leudly diſpoſed, wil ſay as they ſay. Theſe are double tonged, &amp; whoſoeuer are ſuch in them the true feare of God is not remaining.</p>
            <p n="2">2 A ſecond effect and naturall pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perty of the true feare of God is, it cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth a man to deale not with eyeſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice, but faithfully, in al y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> with know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge he take thin hand: it cauſeth him
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:12801:12" rendition="simple:additions"/>to walke not deceiptfully, but with an vpright heart; not in his ordinarie calling alone, but moreouer in the fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing and performance of any god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly buſineſſe otherwiſe lawfully com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted vnto him. The reaſon is, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it placeth the Lord before him ſitting in his throne of iuſtice, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holding all that he doth or thinketh, whereby he is brought &amp; kept in ſuch godly awe, that albeit men coulde not eſpie his falſhood, yet he know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth how the Lord will both ſee and iudge the ſame; wherupon he imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth himſelfe with all diligence to do his worke faithfully, as in the ſight of God. That the true feare of God is of this effect, it is manifeſt, 2. Chron. 19.9. For there we may reade, how Iehoſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phat king of Iuda, laboring the refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation of his whole king dome by due miniſtration of iuſtice, and by diligent preaching of the word, he chargeth the officers to deale vprightly: and minding to ſhew what would be auail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to make them ſo to do, he attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buteth
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:12801:12" rendition="simple:additions"/>this glorious effect to the true feare of God, ſaying, <hi>Thus ſhall ye do in the feare of God,</hi> and by way of expoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion addeth, <hi>faith fully and with a perfect heart:</hi> as if he had ſaid, I may charge you to deale faithfully, but I cannot make you ſo to do: notwithſtanding, that which my commandement can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not worke in you, that the true feare of God (if ye haue the ſame) will effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctually bring to paſſe in you. Now therefore, if ye feare God aright as ye pretend to do, then ſhew it by the true effect of that feare, that is to ſay, by faithfull and vpright dealing in this charge and burthen that is laid vpon you. Let euerie one, of what degree &amp; condition ſoeuer, examine himſelfe by this propertie, &amp; he ſhall eaſily vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtád, whether the true feare of God be reſident with him or no. If ſuch as are in authoritle, be not faithfull in mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtring iuſtice, and ſuppreſſing the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſaries of truth and godlines, it is cuident hereby what they are. If ſuch as are in the miniſterie be not faithfull
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:12801:13" rendition="simple:additions"/>in doing their office, but either diſpéce not the word at all, or deale after the manner of huckſters deceitfully with it, they declare them ſelues to bee void of the true feare of God. If trades men haue and vſe a falſe weight, and a falſe meaſure, or ſeeke to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riche them ſelues by any manner of falſe dealing, there is no queſtion but that ſo long as they continue ſuch and ſo minded, the vnfained and true feare of God hath no dwelling place, nor a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biding in them.</p>
            <p n="3">3 A third effect wherby the true feare of God is made knowne to be in a má, is, that it maketh him not onely to ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parate himſelfe from the defilings and corruptions of the world, when he heareth them rebuked by the word of God, but moreouer ſpeaketh earneſtly to his neighbors, whom he ſeeth en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tangled with ſuch vngodlineſſe, vpon purpoſe and intent to draw them alſo away from thoſe iniquities. Forhe hath euermore his heart meditating vpon the commandemèt of the Lord, which
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:12801:13" rendition="simple:additions"/>chargeth him not onely <hi>to have no fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lovvſhip, vvith the vnfruitfull vvorks of darkneſſe, but moreouver to reproue them,</hi> as is ſet downe Epheſ. 5. This effect of the true feare of God yee may finde in the prophecie of Malachie, chap. 3. 16. For albeit the people of that generati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on were exceeding wicked, yet ſome there were which at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> rebuking &amp; ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monition of the prophet, forſook ſuch wickednes, &amp; laboring to draw others to gither with them, which perſons the prophet noteth to haue bin led to ſuch encouragement of their neighbors by this true feare of God, which the Lord endued thè withal: For ſo lie ſaith, <hi>then</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>they that feared the Lord, ſpake ouery man to his neighbor.</hi> This is a leſſon for you, that can be content in out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward ſhew and appearance to ſubiect your owne necks to the ſweet yoke of chriſtian reformation: yee have heard the prophets of the Lord in the ſpirite and zeale of Malachie, reprooue gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlemen &amp; others for robbing the Lord of his portion, of his tythes, &amp; offrings,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:12801:14" rendition="simple:additions"/>as Malachie did: ye haue heard them roproue miniſters for not keping kno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wledge in their lippes, that the people might aske the lawe of God at theyr mouth, as the Prophet did: yee haue hearde them rebuke many other cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptions, wherein this generation hath farre exceeded and gone beyonde the people of Malachies time: yee haue profited ſo far in outward appearance, that ye lament for theſe iniquities of our time to the eie, and ſeeme to leaue and forſake them your owne ſelues, but yet are in opinion (a great num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of you) howe it is not within the compaſſe of your ſeuerall duties, to la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour in calling other aware from the fame corruptions, out of which yee are eſcaped. Marke therefore this third ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect of the true feare of God, &amp; be well aſſured, that it is euerie mans ductie which will ſhew himſelfe to feare God aright, not onelie to leaue theſe enor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities their own ſelues, but moreouer to exhort euene man his neighbors, be they Gentlemen or other, in eccleſia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fticall
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:12801:14" rendition="simple:additions"/>or temporall vocation, to leaue theſe iniquities with them, and to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come newe men, otherwiſe the true feare of God raigneth not in them.</p>
            <p n="3">3 The third waie and meanes whereby ye may take intelligence of your owne ſoules, whether this true feare of God commanded by S.Peter, dwell in you or no, is by ſuch compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie and fellowſhip as the true feare of God continuallie keepeth. The re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probates, yea the Atheiſts feare God, ſo doe the denils alſo: but it is in ſuch a ſeruile and ſlauiſh manner, that they hate him whom they feare, whereas it is far otherwiſe with them which haue the true feare of God in them: for the true feare of God is, as one verie fitlie tearmeth it, <hi>Tanquam ſeta ſutoria tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bens, poſt ſe filum delectionis,</hi> as it were the ſhoomakers haire drawing after it the threed of loue, which infinite ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples of Gods faithful children, men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned in the Scripture, do confirme &amp; proue: For ſo they feared the Lorde, that they loued him alſo entirely, and
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:12801:15" rendition="simple:additions"/>from the bottome of their hearts. For proofes ſake, to bring one or two, it is reported of Dauid, 2. Sam. 6.9. that hee ſeated the Lord exceeding lie, who not withſtanding Pſal. 116.1. auouched trulie of himſelf, that <hi>he loued the Lord,</hi> Yea and Moſes which in the places be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore mentioned gaue commandement to the people of Iſrael to feare the Lord, doeth alſo charge them <hi>to loue him with all their heart, vvith all their ſoule, and vvith all their might,</hi> Deu. 6.5 which declareth how the true feare of God is accompanied with a loue of him in the ſame partie. So the we muſt not feare God as the deuils and repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bates feare him, neither yet muſt wee feare the almightle with a popiſh kind of feare. How is that, will ſome ſaie, the Papiſts haue a feare of God in the, but it is ſuch a kinde of feare, as is ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>companied with a diſtruſt in God, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomuch that they make it a principle of their religion, how wee muſt feare, and not be bolde of Gods fauor. This detecteth their feare of God not to be
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:12801:15" rendition="simple:additions"/>the true &amp; holy feare commanded by Saint Peter in this place. For the true feare of God is accompanied and joy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with a truſt &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fidence in him, as may be proued cuidentlie in the hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreth and fifteenth Pſalm, the 1. verſe. Eſa 50.10. Beſides, the manifolde ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples of Gods ſcruants endued with a right feare of him, who albeit wreſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling with the multitude of their ſinnes, ſeemed to ſhut the doore of their harts againſt aſſured truſt in the Lorde for a ſeaſon, yet euermore gaue it intertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in the end. By theſe things then (my brethren) ludge of your lelues, if yee feare God ſo that yee hate him, or cannot abide him, &amp; that ye wil not be perſuaded to haue boldnes and aſſured truſt in him to ſaluation, becauſe your conſciences tel you how many &amp; how grieuous your ſinnes are, then haue yee not that feare which Saint Peter ſpeaketh of abiding in you: but if your feare of God bee ioyned with an heartie loue of him, and ye ſo feare his puniſhing iuſtice, that notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:12801:16" rendition="simple:additions"/>ye truſt in his forgiuing mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie, then is the feare of God in you an holie plant, which I beſeech him for Chriſts ſake to raine vppon more and more with the ſweet dew of the word, and to blovv vpon with the quickning breath of his ſpirite, that it may floriſh and bring foorth fruite in you to the end,</p>
            <p>Thus yee ſee (brethren) by vvhat meanes yee may haue vnderſtanding, vvhether ye anſvvere to this comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement of Saint Peter, that is to ſaie, whether ye feare God truelie or no; &amp; hereby alſo ye may knovv vvhat it is to feare God trulie and aright, namely not to be a fearde of the fanſies of our ovvne braine, for then fooles and mad men ſhould feare God truelie; not to tremble onelie at his judgementes, for then the verie vnſenſible mountaines and hils ſhould feare God truelie, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they are readie to tremble at the angrie preſence of the Lord. Pſal. 18.7. not to haue a minde deſperatlie tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented and grieued with the horrour
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:12801:16" rendition="simple:additions"/>of his ovvne ſinnes, for then Iudas and manie of the reprobate ſhoulde haue feared God truelie: not to ſtande in avve ſo of Gods vengeance onelie, that there vpon vve dare not follovve thoſe abhominations vvhich othervviſe our hearts are vvell pleaſed vvith, for then the hypocrites ſhould feare God true<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie: but vpon a due and deep conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of Gods povver, vviſdome, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uidence, iuſtice, &amp;c, to ſtande in ſuch godlie avve of him, that by meanes therof we are brought from the liking and following of vngodlines, to deale faithfullie in all things, to dehort other from thoſe corruptions vvhich our ſelues haue forſaken, and in all this to be ſo affectioned, that vvee delight in the Lord and loue him, at no time vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terlie deſpairing though vve fulfill not our duties ſo fullie as wee ought, but yeelding to that comfort of Gods ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite, vvhereby we are put in hope that God vvil accept our endeuors, though ioyned vvith manie imperfections, as the indeuours, not of ſlaues, but of his
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:12801:17" rendition="simple:additions"/>faithfull and obedient children.</p>
            <p>This is now the true feare of God, whereof Saint Peter ſpeaketh, &amp; theſe are ſome meanes whereby yee may know and diſcerne whether the ſame bee in your ſelues or other. And foraſ much as there is nothing more to bee deſired at the hands of almightie God, then that all men may atraine to this feare, &amp; retaine it alſo cuen to the end, it is needfull for vs to conſider what thoſe things are which may ſerue as the ordinatie meanes to draw men vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, and continue men in this true feare of God.</p>
            <p>There are then two eſpecial things which are of great force both to make men feare God trulie, and alſo to keep and preſerue in them that grace and gift of God: wherof the firſt is the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellencie and peereleſſe dignitie and worthineſſe of this grace. The ſecond is the incomparable bleſſings of God which foolowe the ſame, and art promiſed to as manie as abide in the it.</p>
            <pb n="25" facs="tcp:12801:17" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p> The worthines of this feare of God the Scripture fetteth foorth, in that it ſpoiling the men of this worlde of thoſe gracious titles wherein they make all true honour and commenda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to ſtand and conſiſt, it attributeth them notwithſtanding to thoſe that feare the Lord.</p>
            <p>It is a thing which men moſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire of all other things, to be truly wiſe, inſomuch that for the bare name ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, infinite perſons of all ages and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees, haue thought neither any coſt il beſtowed, nor anie labour ill taken, ſo they might be reputed of the worlde for wiſe men; naithles the world could neuer attaine to this in deed: For when the iudgment is brough to the throne of God, they are all condemed of folly as Saint Paul declareth 1. Corinth. 1. wher he ſaith, <hi>hovv the vviſdome of this vvorld is fooliſhnes vvith God.</hi> In the meane ſeaſon, ſuch as feare God truly are by the holy Ghoſt himſelfe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced to be rightly and truly wiſe. For the patient Iob ſaieth, <hi>The feare</hi>
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:12801:18" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <hi>of the Lord is wiſedome in deede,</hi> chap. 28 Whereunto agreeth Salomon, who Prouerbs 1. auoucheth the feare of the Lord to be <hi>Reſhith dagnath,</hi> the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of knovvledge, or rather as vvee ſaie in our common ſpeech, the chiefe point of knovvledge or head knovv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge: and again in his fifteenth chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter he ſaith, <hi>The feare of the Lord is the inſtruction of vviſedome.</hi> Whereby we may perceiue howe they onelie are wiſe in deede which feare the Lorde, &amp; al other the children of follie and mad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, ſo excellent and ſurpaſſing a thing is the feare of God. Beſides that, the Scripture calling vpon men to ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctifie the Lord, that is, to worſhip him with ſuch a kinde of worſhip, as wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by he may be declared and knowen to be holie, doth require this true feare of God for performance thereof. For ſo the Prophet Eſaie chapter 8, comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth men <hi>to ſanctfre the Lorde of hoſtes:</hi> and to ſhew how that ſhould be done, he addeth immediatlie by wale of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition, <hi>Let him bee your feare,</hi> by that
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:12801:18" rendition="simple:additions"/>meanes adorning the true feare of God, with that moſt honorable name and title of ſanctifying the Lorde of hoſts. Adde hereunto, that the prophet Eſay chap. 33.6, maketh account how <hi>The feare of God is a treaſure to the god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,</hi> enriching them aboundantly which haue it, in the ſight of God; whereup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon it muſt needes enſue, that they which are deſtitute of this grace, are ſtarke beggers before God, howſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer they flow &amp; ſwimme in outward wealth and proſperitie. Thus ye ſee of what great dignitie the true feare of God is, which ought to rauiſh you with a deſire both to ſubject your ſelues to this commandement of S. Peter, that the holy Ghoſt mare worke this true feare in your heartes; and alſo to take heed, that the manifolde entiſementes of the worlde and fleſh which are laid as baites to beguile ſillie ſoules eueric where, bereaue you not of it beeing once ſetled in your hearts, conſidering how excellent a thing it is in the iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the holy Ghoſt.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <pb n="34" facs="tcp:12801:19" rendition="simple:additions"/> 2 Concerning the bleſſings which God hath promiſed to thoſe that feare him, they are ſo great, that greater cannot he. For what is it (brethren) that your heartes would or can wiſh or deſire? would yee be deliuered from all ſuch enimies at home or abroad, as do ſecke by ſubtiltie or crueltie to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reaue you of life, of libertie, of the truth, yea and of God himſelfe? Then <hi>Feare the Lord</hi> (ſaith the ſpirite) <hi>and he will deliuer you out of the hands of your enimies.</hi> 2. <hi>Reg.</hi> 17.39. Would yee haue your poſteritie that they ſhall ſtand vp in your place ſucceſſiuely, to encreaſe and proſper: <hi>Feare the Lord</hi> (ſaith the holy ghoſt) <hi>and it ſhall go well with you and with your children af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter you for evermore, Deut.</hi> 5.29. would yee be ſtrong againſt all aſſaultes of our ſpirituall enimies? Feare the Lord, and yee ſhall be ſo. For (as Salomon ſaith) <hi>In the feare of the Lord is aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuredneſſe of ſtrength. Prouerb.</hi> 14. <hi>and the</hi> 26. <hi>verſe.</hi> Againe, would yee be out of doubt which is the right
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:12801:19" rendition="simple:additions"/>and true waie, among ſo great di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſitie of opinions as are now in the world? <hi>Feare the Lorde, and he vvill teach you in the vvaie that ye ſhall chooſe, yea the ſecretes of the Lorde ſhall be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong you if yee feare him, and he vvill shevv you his couenant. Pſal.</hi> 25.11.13. To conclude, will yee be bleſſed, that is to ſay, in a ſtate perfited with a ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thering togither of all good thinges? Feare God, and yee ſhall be ſo. For (as Dauid ſaith) <hi>Bleſſed are they that feare the Lord. Pſal.</hi> 112.1.</p>
            <p>For all this, the greateſt part of the world regard not to feare the Lord, but haue their hearts filled with con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt of him: whereof to conſider the cauſes and remedies is verie needfull, that we may take heed, and giue obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to this precept of S.Peter.</p>
            <p n="1">1 One cauſe then why men feare not the Lord, is the want of tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching and hearing the word of God, by which as by an inſtrument ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctified to that purpoſe, the Lorde diſtilleth his feare into the heartes
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:12801:20" rendition="simple:additions"/>of men. This may be gathered out of Deut. 31. where Moſes giuing charge to Ioſua concerning the reading of the Law in the eares of the whole congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation of Iſrael, ſheweth alſo where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it was to be done; namely, that <hi>they might learne to feare the Lord their God. verſ.</hi> 12.13. If then the publiſhing of the word be the meanes to learne men the feare of the Lord, it muſt needs be, that the want of this bleſſing is a reaſon why manie are deſtitute of the true feare of God. For remedie wherof none other way can be found, than for the miniſter diligently to teach, and the people as diligently to heare the word of the Lord.</p>
            <p n="2">2 A ſecond reaſon why men feare not the Lord is, becauſe their hearts are poſſeſſed with a ſtrong imaginati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, that it is in vaine to feare God. This cauſe of mens not fearing the Lord, the Prophet Malachie declareth, Chapt. 3. for hauing ſpoken of certaine which feared not the Lord, verſ. 5. he doth af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terward ſhew their reaſon that per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:12801:20" rendition="simple:additions"/>them to ſet the Lord at naught and to giue out ſtoure words againſt him, which was, becauſe in their cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt iudgement, <hi>it was in vaine to ſerue God, and it was no profite to them that they walked humblie before the Lord of hostes, verſ.</hi> 14. Againſt this peſtilent perſwaſion which leadeth manie now adayes to the contempt of God, a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medie of ſoueraigne effect is, the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration of thoſe promiſes before propounded to them that feare the Lord, which will be then more effectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, when we ſet before our ſelues in our minds as on a theatre or ſtage, the perſons of many that feared the Lord, as of Abraham, Ieſeph, Moſes, Dauid, &amp;c. enioying part of theſe promiſes in this life, and now fully poſſeſſed of the reſt in the kingdome of God.</p>
            <p n="3">3 A third matter, where upon many take occaſion to neglect &amp; caſt away the feare of God, is a groſſe conceit of the nature of God, inducing them to thinke that the Lord ſeeth not what men do in the earth, and that they may
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:12801:21" rendition="simple:additions"/>do what they will for him. After this ſort the wicked in Iobs time ſurmiſed, that <hi>God vvas ſo hidden vvith the darke cloudes, that he could not iudge thorough them,</hi> and therefore they deſpiſed him. And ſo the vngodly in the dayes of David <hi>ſpake fiercely, and the vvorkers of iniquitie vaunted themſelues against God,</hi> and all was vpon this perſwaſion, <hi>That the Lord did not ſee it, the God of Iacob did not marke it. Pſal.</hi> 94. Againſt this enchantment, that it may not preuaile in mens hearts to leade them away from the feare of God, it helpeth much to conſider, that <hi>nothing is hid from the eyes of God. Heb.</hi> 4. <hi>that he ſear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth all heartes, and vnderstandeth all the thoughts of the minde.</hi> 2. <hi>Chron.</hi> 28.9. that it is a brutiſh follie to thinke that <hi>he vvhich planted the care should not heare, and he vvhich formed the eye should not ſee, Pſal.</hi> 94. which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration, if it be deepely imprinted in our minds, it will make vs to ſee that the darke cloudes are no hinde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance to the Lord, but that he behol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:12801:21" rendition="simple:additions"/>all things, even the verie purpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of the heart, and therefore is the more to be feared. 1. King. the eight chapter and 39.</p>
            <p n="4">4 A fourth reaſon why men regard not the feare of God, is becauſe they ſee themſelues &amp; others, who are with out al true reuerence of the almightie, to proſper well enough in the world, whileſt they that fear the Lord, endure and paſſe through many aduerſities &amp; troubles. This reaſon of the wickeds contempt of God, the prophet Dauid ſaw &amp; acknowledged, Pſa. 73. <hi>For why</hi> (as he ſaith) <hi>becauſe the vvicked come not in trouble, neither are plauged vvith other men, becauſe there are no bandes in their death, but they are luſty and ſtrong, therefore they glorie in their pride as in a golden chaine, they talke preſumptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly, and they ſet their mouth against heaven,</hi> That is to ſay, they ſpeake in defiance of God him ſelfe. In like ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner he ſaith of the vngodlie. Pſalm. 55.19. that <hi>Becauſe they have no changes, therefore they feare not God.</hi> To expell
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:12801:22" rendition="simple:additions"/>which poiſoned conceits out of mens hearts, there is not anie more conueni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent remedie, than to <hi>marke the vvaie of the vvorld, vvherin vvicked men (vvhich ſaie vnto God, depart from vs) haue vval<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked, and how they haue ben cut downe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore their time, vvhoſe foundation vvas as ariuer that ouerflovved.</hi> Iob. 22. To conſider with Dauid, that <hi>the Lord hath ſet ſuch wicked ones in ſlipperie places,</hi> &amp; that the conceit which they haue of their proſperous eſtate, is no better then the fanſie of a dreaming man, who in his ſleepe imagineth himſelfe and other to bee riche and in good caſe, but when he a waketh he findeth it no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing ſo. Pſal. 73. Briefly, to conſider that the leſſe trouble they ſuſtain here, the more torment is behinde, and the more bleſſings or prouocations to the feare of God they haue receiued, the leſſe mercie ſhall they finde, becauſe they abuſed them to ſtrengthen their heartes in contempte of the Lord.</p>
            <p>Theſe are the chiefe things which
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:12801:22" rendition="simple:additions"/>cauſe men to reiect the feare of the al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mightie: theſe are the ſtones whereat they ſtumble, and the rockes againſt which they make ſhipwrack, which e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerie one muſt take heed of that is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſirous to walk in the obedience of this commandement, and to <hi>feare God,</hi> as S. Peter counſelleth him to doe.</p>
            <p>Thus haue ye heard vpon occaſion of Saint Peters words, exhorting vs to feare God, both how yee may knowe when ye feare him aright, what may ſerue to inflame you with an earneſt deſire to feare him truelie, and what cauſeth men not to feare the Lord. Let vs now learne other leſſons miniſtred to vs in the ſame precept.</p>
            <p>Whereas the feare of God which is not in the profeſſion of the mouth, but in the inward affection and feeling of the heart, is here by Saint Peter com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded to thoſe which before hee cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth <hi>apeople ſet at libertie, to ſhevv forth the vertues of him which hath called the out of darknes into his meruailous light,</hi> that is to ſaie, vnto the profeſſors
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:12801:23" rendition="simple:additions"/>of chriſtianitie: we muſt make our rec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>koning that would gladly be taken for chriſtians, howe it is enough for vs to ſpeake &amp; talke of the maieſtie, good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, prouidence, power, &amp; other ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous attributes aſcribed to God, but eſpeciallie it is required, that we be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardlie touched in our ſoules with a feare and reuerence of him: yea and verily they which can only ſay well of God, and are not endued with a true feare of him, are no better chriſtians in compariſon, than that chriſtian man which the painter painteth vppon a cloth or wal. For the painters chriſtian is ſoberly apparelled, and made to loke after the ſaddeſt manner: moreo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer, he hath a ſcrowle comming out of his mouth, wherein is written ſome goodly ſentence of the Scripture ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of God, and yet for all this he is no true chriſtian, becauſe he lacketh that which the painter can not giue him, that is to ſay, the true feare of God; and ſo theſe (brethren) which make an outward faire ſhew &amp; ſpeake
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:12801:23" rendition="simple:additions"/>well of God, are not true chriſtians, if they wa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t the true feare of God which is grafted in the heart, and is a ſpeciall thing required in a true chriſtian man, as by the precept of ſaint Peter giuen to chriſtian men appeareth.</p>
            <p>Beſides this leſſon, there are other profitable inſtructions which are of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered vnto vs out of the order of this precept, <hi>Feare God,</hi> compared with that which followeth, <hi>honor the king.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As firſt of all, ſaint Peter, ſetteth this precept before, <hi>Feare God,</hi> and the other after, <hi>honor the king:</hi> where by he inſinuateth &amp; giueth vs to vnderſtand, how the feare &amp; obedience of God is to be preferred to the honour and obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of princes; the very ſame rule &amp; leſſon which S. Peter &amp; S. Iohn togi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther teach vs Act. 4.19. namely, <hi>That it is right in the ſight of God to obey him ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</hi> as co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> reſon alſo maketh vs to know &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſe. For the ſouerain muſt be obeied before the lieutenant, the L. of the houſe before the ſteward of it, the maiſter before the ſeruaunt,
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:12801:24" rendition="simple:additions"/>and thérfore God before all princes, and rather than all princes and poten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tates in the worlde, becauſe God is the ſoueraine king, and they are his Lieu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenants, God is the maiſter, &amp; they are his ſeruantes: which admoniſheth vs to attempt nothing for any prince vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the ſame, which ouerthroweth, impaireth, or vndermineth the flouri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing eſtate of the true feare of God, either in our ſelues or in any other, leaſt we bee called into iudgement for ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing the creature with contempt of the creator, and preferring man before God.</p>
            <p>An other leſſon is taught vs in this order of preceptes, deliuered by ſaint Peter in this place. For by ſetting <hi>Feare God</hi> before <hi>honour the king,</hi> he inſinua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth vnto vs, howe that if princes will looke to haue true and faithfull ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects, ſuch as will haue care from the verie bottome of their hearts to yeelde them that due honor which is to them belonging, them muſt they firſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uide, that they be trained vp in the true
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:12801:24" rendition="simple:additions"/>feare of the almightie: for it is hard to ſay, that he which feareth not God a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right, will or can euer honor his prince truly.</p>
            <p n="1">1 For why? Firſt of all, that which eſpeciallie mooueth men ſo to honour their prince, is the commandement &amp; feare of God, as ſaint Peter ſaith be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in this chapter, they doe it <hi>for the Lordes ſake:</hi> whereupon it followeth that if a man haue not the feare of God him ſelfe, which is the cauſe of his faithfull obedience to his prince, it can not well be that he ſhould vnfainedlie and trulie honour his ſoueraine, which is an effect of that feare of God.</p>
            <p n="2">2 Our ſoueraine Chriſt in the para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of the wicked iudge, noting the ſumme of his vngratiouſnes, vttereth it in this manner, <hi>he neither</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red God nor reuerenced man,</hi> Luke. 18.2. as noting the ſame leſſon which I haue ſaid vnto vs.</p>
            <p n="3">3 That is moſt plaine which we read lerem. 32. where the holie Gho<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſt (who is beſt acquainted with our na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture)
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:12801:25" rendition="simple:additions"/>doth ſhew and declare, howe we are of ſuch a condition, that vnleſſe we be retained and kept in order and awe by the feare of God, we will fall away euen from God him ſelfe. For thus the ſpirt of God by the prophet ſaith, <hi>I will put feare in their heartes that they ſhall not depart from me:</hi> as if he ſaid, I know that men will not faithfully con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue, no not in my ſeruice which am their God and creator, vnleſſe they be indued with my true feare: and ſhall we then thinke (brethren) that men which haue not the true feare of God planted in their hearts, can euer faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully and truly honor their prince?</p>
            <p n="4">4 It is not to be looked for (dere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly beloued) that he wil regard the bla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of a candle, which is not moued with the moſt glorious brightneſſe of the ſunne. It is not for anie to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade men, that he will euer regarde the value of a pennie, which deſpiſeth the full ſtorehouſe of all riche things, &amp;c. no more is it likely that he which feareth not the God of vnſpeakeable
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:12801:25" rendition="simple:additions"/>glory, will giue any vnfained honor to his prince, &amp;c. the ſumme is, it is hard to deeme otherwiſe, but that he which is deſtitute of the fear of God, whether by meanes of ignorance or conte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſnes can or wil euer honor his prince truly. I deny not, but the Lord ſo re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraineth oftentimes many godles per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons with the bridle of a certaine feare that they breake not forth into outra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious rebellio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> againſt their prince, but rather ſtand ſtoutly vnto him euen vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the death; which is nothing againſt that I ſay: for I ſhew what nature be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing not tilled with this true feare of God ordinarily yeeldeth, not what God againſt the force of nature many times worketh. Againe, I ſpeake of that honouring of the prince which is a chriſtian vertue and a worke of the ſpirit of ſanctification, not of that ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice whereunto many are brought by the ſpirit (as they tearme it) repreſſing vices.</p>
            <p>They that are gentlemen, &amp; by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of their calling haue neceſſarily
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:12801:26" rendition="simple:additions"/>to retaine manie in their ſeruice to waite vpon them, let them conſider this well that I ſay. If they feede and cloth their ſeruants well, but teach them not the feare of God, out of que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion they do nothing elſe but harten men, and make them ſtrong to rebell againſt their Prince. Yee that are mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters alſo, conſider this well, and let it make you diligent to inſtruct your flockes in the true feare of God. Alas (brethren) are they not too many alre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die, which in helliſh madneſſe without all feare of God, go about to bereaue out gracious ſoueraine of her life, the whole realme of peace, the goſpel of paſſage? Alas than, why ſhould ye alſo ſinne againſt God and againſt your owne ſoules, by increaſing the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of rebellious and diſloyal perſons? Ye will ſay peraduenture, we do it not: yes verely, if yee teach not your people diligently the fear of the Lord. For vnleſſe men haue their hearts poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſed with the true feare of God, they will not honor their Prince truely.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="49" facs="tcp:12801:26" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <head>Honor the king.</head>
               <p>Ye haue hither to heard me patient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie, concerning the feare of God: heare me nowe (I beſeech you) concerning our dutie toward the king. Saint Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters commandement is, that kings and princes ſhoulde be honoured; which that it maie be more forcible both to teach vs and alſo to win vs, I thinke it needefull at this ſeaſon, after my rude and diſordered maner, to deliuer vnto you theſe foure eſpeciall points.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1 <hi>What it is to honor the king.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2 <hi>Which are the partes of this honor.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>3 <hi>Of whom this honor is to be rendred</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>4 <hi>For what cauſes men are to yeld the ſame.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <p>Honor, in this place, in the Greeke called <hi>Timè,</hi> is a godly acknowleging and regarding of princes as the chie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt and choſen inſtruments of God, for the maintenance as well of ciuill, as of eccleſiaſticall ſociety. Conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der what I ſay. To honour the king, is firſt to acknowledge him for the annointed of the Lord, and alſo for
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:12801:27" rendition="simple:additions"/>our annointed: neither that by wordes alone, but by ſuch other meanes alſo as we are able, accordingly as we read of the people of Iſrael in their receuing of Saul. For they did not only ſhowre altogether, ſaying, <hi>God ſane the king,</hi> but moreouer all the godlie deſpoled browght him preſentes. 1. Sam. 10.24. 27. and they which did not ſo, are no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by the ſpirit of God for wicked me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; are held guilty of deſpiſing him be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the iudgement ſeat of the almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie. Moreouer, we muſt make ſuchac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counte of them, that we ſet not them a footeſtoole here in earth, and other a throne to ſit ouer them: (as the Papiſts make the King the vaſſal of their pope) but we muſt vnfeinedly confeſſe them with S. Peter the chiefeſt perſons, &amp; to them giue the ſoueraigntie and prehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minence here in this worlde, aſſuring our ſelues, that he is Antechriſt, which exalteth himſelf aboue them. 2. Theſſ. 2.4. To conclude, we muſt not looke vpon them as vpon diſguiſed Kinges, browght forth on a ſtage or theater,
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:12801:27" rendition="simple:additions"/>which beſide their gaie garments and great wordes haue nothing in them a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue the common ſorte, but we muſt receaue them as the chiefeſt &amp; higheſt Ambaſſadours of God, ſent among vs with largeſt and moſt ample power and authoritie, yea and ſuche power and authoritie, as whereof the beſt, the wiſeſt, the richeſt, the godlieſt, ſhall haue neede to maintaine them in outward ſocieties whether ciuill or eccleſiaſticall, conſidering they are thereunto ſanctified and ſent of the Lorde, whoſe onely bleſſing enableth euerie man to worke the good of his people.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The partes of his honour which here is commanded by Saint Peter to be done vnto the Kinge, are three, to wit, <hi>Reuerence, Obedience, and Paying of ſuch tribute,</hi> or other dewes or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nenewes, as belong to a perſon of that calling and dignitie.</p>
               <p>Vnder the name of reuerencing the prince, we vnderſtande that men ought both to thinke honourablie
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:12801:28" rendition="simple:additions"/>of the prince, to pray for him, as alſo to frame and diſpoſe all their outward geſtures and ſpeech in ſuch ſort, that it may carrie with it and in it a ſigne of their vnfained ſubiection to ſuch per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons.</p>
               <p>Of mens reuerend thinking of ſuch, we reade in the booke of the preacher chap. 10. where the wiſedome of God in Solomo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> giueth charge on this wife, <hi>Curſe not</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>the king no not in thy thought.</hi> For the bridling of our toong from all vnreuerende woordes againſt ſuch, Moſes giueth a commandement Exod. 22.28. on this manner, <hi>Thou ſhalt not</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>curſe the ruler of thy peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple.</hi> Whereunto adde that ſaint Peter 2.Epiſt. 2.2.10.11. and ſaint Iude alſo do account them to be vngodly per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons and bringers in of damnable he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſie, which ſpeake ouil of thoſe which are in dignity: yea, they account them as preſumptuous perſons daring to ſpeake that in contempt of princes &amp; princely gouernement, which the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels durſt not ſpeake againſt the verie
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:12801:28" rendition="simple:additions"/>deuill him ſelfe. Of mans duty praying for princes, we reade 1. Tim. 2. Of the reuerend geſture which we are to vſe towards ſuch perſons, we haue exáple in Nathan the prophet, who made o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beiſance before king Dauid <hi>vppon his face vnto the grounde.</hi> 1. Reg. 1.23. Theſe are continuall and ordinarie rules and examples, for the gouerning &amp; direc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of our behauiour toward perſons of that authority.</p>
               <p>Some will ſay, if it be ſo, then did Eliſha offende in calling Ichoram the <hi>murtherers ſonne.</hi> 2. Reg. 6.32. and our Sauiour him ſelfe in calling Herode a fox. Luke 13.32. then alſo did the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foreſaid Eliſha breake the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of God in demeaning him ſelfe ſo towarde the ſaid Ichoram, that hee would not once haue looked vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> him had it not bin for regard that he had to the preſence of Ichoſaphat 2. Re. 3. the was Michaiah to be reproued for ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king in manner of deriſion to Ahab. 2. Chron. 18. Hereunto I anſwer, how the precepts &amp; examples before ſet down,
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:12801:29" rendition="simple:additions"/>bind vs, and not the Lorde, who maie ſharpely controll the princes of this world for their miſdoings, &amp; alſo may vſe the ſeruice of whome it pleaſeth him in that behalſe, neither ſhall he ſinne, that hauing the extraordinarie commandement of the Lord, ſpeaketh ſo vnto them in Gods name, which yet is no common rule for euerie bodie, neither yet for him at all ſeaſons. For more cuidence herein, I vſe this fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liar ſimilitude: if ſome great monarch hauing vnder him manie prouinces, &amp; ech it own king as his lieutenant, make it a common lawe, that no perſon of what degree ſocuer within his domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, ſhall behaue himſelf vnreuerent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in worde or decde againſt anie his lieutenants: this letteth not, but that the afore ſaid monarch hauing know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge and intelligence of anie his lieu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenantes vngodly practiſes, may him ſelfe commande whome hee thinkes good as Ambaſſadour from him to go vnto that lieutenant, and in his name to giue him ſuch rebuke as be deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uech,
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:12801:29" rendition="simple:additions"/>and ſuche tearmes of diſgrace as are meete for him, which yet eueric one may not doe, neither yet that Ambaſſadour without the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement of his monarch. In like ſort, foraſmuch as God is the onely monarch of the whole worlde, and all princes his lieutenants within their ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ucrall dominions: though he haue ſet it downe as a common law for his ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects, that is, for all other men, that no perſon in the world ſhall once dare to vſe the prince vnreuerently in worde or deede, yet this letteth not but that when princes deſpiſe and breake the commandements of God whoſe lieu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenants they are, the Lorde may make who me he liſteth his Ambaſſadour to them ward, &amp; cauſe the ſaid Ambaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dor (without any his offenſe) to rebuke them with what hard maner of ſpeach foeuer, according to their deſertes, it ſhall pleaſe his diuine maieſty to put into the mouth of that his meſſenger, which yet euery one may not do, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther that Ambaſſadour, be he prophet
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:12801:30" rendition="simple:additions"/>or miniſter without ſuch commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. Thus we ſee the Prophets and extraordinary meſſengers of the Lord, as Eliſha, Micaiah, &amp;c. cleere from fault, becauſe they had the word of the Lord ſo to doe, and yet no man autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſed by their example to ſpeake or do his wicked pleaſure againſt his prince. Which euerie true ſubiect is to note &amp; obſerue, not onelie for intent that the deuill may not leade him by miſcon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction of Gods word, to vnreuerent handling of his ſoueraigne, but moreo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer that we may vnderſtand for a ſure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, that they are nothing elſe but de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uilliſh treachers and helliſh blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, where with our Engliſh traitours haue oppoſed themſelues againſt our annointed of the Lorde, calling her <hi>v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurping competitour,</hi> and laboring by all wicked pollicie to ſhed her bloud, in conſideration they had no commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment from the Lorde, neither yet fuſt cauſe ſo to do.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The ſecond parte of the kings honour is obedience, which is <hi>a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forming</hi>
                  <pb n="57" facs="tcp:12801:30" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <hi>of all the Princes lavvfull com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandements</hi> (that is to ſaie, which iuſtle not againſt the truth of Gods worde) <hi>ioyned vvith a quiet ſuffering at their handes for vnlavvfull things refuſed.</hi> And for the firſt point, that the Prince is to be honored with ſueh fulfilling of all his lawfull and godly ordinances, by the Scripture may bee plainlie ſhewed and declared vnto vs. For in as much as the worde of God maketh reckoning how the king is the chiefeſt of all here in this world, 1. Pet. 2. it were abſurd to thinke, how the ſpirite of God woulde haue leſſe ſubmiſſion rendered to ſuch an one, then it chargeth ſeruantes to yeld to their common maiſters. Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vpon it followeth, that ſeeing S. Paule cammandeth ſeruants <hi>to be obedient vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them that are their maiſters according vnto the fleſh in all things,</hi> that is to ſaie, in all lawfull things, Colloſsians the third Chapter and two and twentith verſe. Much more muſt men be readie to obey the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mandeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of the prince in all things that are lawfull and god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:12801:31" rendition="simple:additions"/>conſidering that if they do not ſo obey, foraſmuch as obedience is one part of the princes honor, they do plain ly diſhonour the prince in that point.</p>
               <p n="2">2 In this caſe we find a notable ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample in the booke of Ioſhua, chap. 16.17.18. For whereas the people of the Lorde perceaued that Ioſhua was full of the ſpirit of wiſdom, and that he was annointed of the Lord to be their gonernor now after the death of Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, they knowing what dutie they ought vnto one in that place &amp; digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, with great reuerence ſubmit them ſelues vnto him, &amp; make promiſe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Lord to obey him in all things lawful. For thus they ſay vnto him, <hi>All that thou haſt commanded vs will vve do, and vvhether ſoener thou ſendest vs vve will go, As we obeyed Moſos in all things ſo vvill vve obey thee, and vvhoſoeuer ſhall rebell against thy commanlement, &amp; vvill not obey thy vvordes in all that thou commandeſt him, let him be put to death.</hi> This is the promiſe of the people, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proued of God, receaued of Ioſhua, ſot
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:12801:31" rendition="simple:additions"/>downe in the worde for a preſident to after generations, whereby we are put out of all dout, that the prince is to be honored with fulfilling &amp; performing of all his lawfull &amp; godly commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments. That which I have ſhewed you in doctrine, I will alſo make cuidet by example in our owne ſelues. And firſt I ſuppoſe, how hir maieſty by ſtatute or ſome other princely meanes, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded in the firſt, or ſome other yere paſt of her reigne, or if not comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded her ſelfe, yet ratified ſome ſtatute of her noble an ceſtours, commanding that after ſuch time no vnlearned and vnſufficient miniſter ſhould be admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to preach the worde or to admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter the ſacraments. This if it were ſo, it were a moſt lawfull commandement, becauſe it accordeth and is agreeable with the word of God, which not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly alloweth none other perſon to haue cure of ſoules, but ſuch a one as whoſe lippes do keepe knowledge, and from whoſe mouth the people may aſke &amp; haue the law of the Lord, Malach. 2.
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:12801:32" rendition="simple:additions"/>1. Tim. 3: but alſo teacheth how if the ſalt, that is the miniſter, haue loſt his ſaltneſſe, that is, the abillitie to teach the people of God, he is thence forth (not to be imployed to meaner partes of that calling, but) good for nothing in that office, but to be caſt out and trodden vnder foote. Conſidering than how this commandement were moſt lawfull, whoſoeuer ſhould after the time aforeſaid wittingly and wilfully make by ſuch vnlearned miniſter, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>obey; the lawfull commandement of the Prince, and conſequently ſo farre forth diſhonoreth his Prince. The reaſon is apparant; namely, becauſe obedience or fulfilling of the Princes lawfull commandements and lawes, is one part of the Princes honour, which cannot be denyed him but ſo much of his princely honor muſt be denied him alſo. In like maner I ſay of ſuch law of our Soueraine, as commandeth cuerie ſubject of this realme to come and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſort to church at time ſanctified and ſet a part for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame purpoſe by the Lord;
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:12801:32" rendition="simple:additions"/>it is a moſt lawfull &amp; godly comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement: For it is euery way agreeable to the word of God, commanding all men <hi>to keepe his Sabbathes and to reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence his ſanctuarie, Leuit.</hi> 19.30. where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore when our Engliſh Papiſts refuſe this, they do (for the reaſon aforeſaid) ſo far forth diſhonor the Prince which commandeth it. The like may be ſaid of many things commanded in our lawes, which being compared with the word of God, appeare to be moſt law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and godly.</p>
               <p>But here, ſome flauering courtier will ſay, you auouch that obedience (that is a fulfilling of the princes law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full commandementes) is a part of the princes honor: tell me this I pray you, do not they diſobey the king and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently diſhonor him, which do not whatſoeuer he commandeth.</p>
               <p>No truely: for true and chriſtian o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience whereby the prince is hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, is a performing of lawfull comma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dements. If anie thing therefore that is commanded be vnlawfull, and againſt
<gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="60" facs="tcp:12801:33" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="61" facs="tcp:12801:33" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <pb n="62" facs="tcp:12801:34" rendition="simple:additions"/>the words of God, the perſourmance thereof can not truely be called by the name of true obedience (whereof we ſpeake) And as the doing of ſuch vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawfull matters can not ſhrwde it ſelfe vnder the name of obedience: ſo if we looke narrowely and neerelye vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to it, it is nothing els but an vngodlie prouoking of the Lorde to ſhorten the life of princes, yea and on our parts which commit or admit ſuch vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawfull things, ſo many furderances &amp; thruſtinges forward of the prince vnto death as may eaſily be diſcerned by that of Salomon Proue. 28.2. where he ſayth, <hi>For the tranſgreſſion of a land ther are manis princes thereof,</hi> meaning that ſinne, which is a tranſgreſſion of the law of God, is a cauſe wherefore the princes liues are ſhortned through the iuſt vengeance of God, either againſt the prince chiefly as one vnworthy to rule Gods people any longer, if the people haue ſinned at his commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, or againſt the people as vnwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy to haue a good prince any longer,
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:12801:34" rendition="simple:additions"/>if they haue ſinned contrary to the princes will and pleaſure.</p>
               <p n="2">2. For the ſecond point of true obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to the king, ſome will further aſke &amp; ſay, But what if a prince wil en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer men to doe otherwiſe then God hath commanded, and to commit ſuch thinges as God hath forbidden vpon paine of puniſhment or death may not here one withſtande their prince by open warre, rather then to ſuffer ſuch puniſhment vniuſtly at his hand?</p>
               <p>I anſwer, woe vnto ſuch thoughts as trayterous &amp; accurſed, refolled by the martirdomes of ſo many thouſandes, as both in the Scripture and other eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſtical hiſtories are read, when vnlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full thinges were commanded them, or lawfull thinges forbidden them v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon paine of ſuch puniſhment to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſue and followe, to ſuffer quietely (which is the ſeconde pointe of true obedience to the prince) and not fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſly to riſe or rebell againſt them: and therefore trayterous aboue mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure were and are the practiſes of ſuch
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:12801:35" rendition="simple:additions"/>as being commanded nothing but that which was godly, haue indeuoured to bereaue our Soueraine of life by open rebellion, rather than they would be obedient to iuſt lawes &amp; commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments in the feare of the Lorde, as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came godlie and chriſtian ſubiectes to do without grudging.</p>
               <p n="3">3 The third part of the princes ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour is, paying of tribute and other ſuch money or commodities of the worlde, as by kingly right and autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie belongeth vnto him. This our Sauiour him ſelfe teacheth both by doctrine, and alſo by example. His doctrine is to be found written, Mark. 12.17. where he ſaith, <hi>Giue vnto Ceſar that vvhich is Ceſars,</hi> ſpeaking there of tribute, as it is manifeſt. For he was de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded whether it were lawful to pay tribute vnto Ceſar or no: whereupon he requeſting the demanders to ſhew him a pennie, and aſking whoſe image and ſuperſcription the pennie had on it, when they anſwered, Ceſars, than he replyed, ſaying, <hi>Giue therefore vnto</hi>
                  <pb n="65" facs="tcp:12801:35" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <hi>Ceſar that vvhich is Ceſars, and vnto God that vvhich is Gods.</hi> His example is to be found Matth. 17.27. where he himſelfe, albeit the heire of all things, yet being now in the forme of a ſeruant &amp; vnder worldly iuriſdiction, payeth polemony to the officers which came vnto him for it. In like manner S. Paul Rom. 13. hauing prooued by ſundrie verie forcible arguments, how all men are to be ſubiect vnto the higher powers, when he commeth to declare by what practiſe we are to ſhew the ſame ſubiection, he inferreth on this wiſe, <hi>Giue therefore</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>tribute to vvhom tribute appertaineth:</hi> as decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring thereby how one cannot denie the king his tribute, but he therewith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all diſhonoureth the ſame king, and denieth him that ſubiection which the Lord alloweth him in his word.</p>
               <p>Concerning the third point of our former diuiſion, which was touching the perſons who are to yeeld this ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour to the king, they are people of al degrees and callings whatſocuer, of
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:12801:36" rendition="simple:additions"/>whom the Prince demandeth the ſame and impoſeth it as from the Lord, for this the plaine words of the ſcripture do exact and ſtraightly commande, Rom. 13. <hi>Let euery ſoule be ſubiect</hi> (ſaith ſaint Paul) <hi>to the higher powers,</hi> and S. Peter hath a notable reaſon hereof comprehended in one word, when he calleth the king the chiefe among all other. For he that is chiefeſt of all, is to be honoured of all, of what eſtate or calling ſo euer they be. The king or Prince is the chiefe of all, and therefore all other parties, whether they ſerue the Lord in ciuill or eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſticall vocations, are to honour the Prince in manner aforeſaid.</p>
               <p n="2">2 This hath plentiful and ſufficient proofe out of thoſe manifold examples of the word, wherein (as it were a ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble) are ſet before vs, and deſcribed all degrees of people honouring the king or prince as be commeth them, ſo that none can plead any right of im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munitie in this behalfe. If one were a Patriarch, he hath an example to reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:12801:36" rendition="simple:additions"/>re<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce &amp; honor the king miniſtred &amp; gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> him in Abraha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, who bowed him ſelf before Ephron, and before his people, Ge. 2.3. If a miniſter of the church, he is taught to reuere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce &amp; honor the king by the example of Aaron, who ſubmitteth himſelf to Moſes, Nu. 12.11. of the prieſt that obeied Saul, 1. Sa. 14.18.19. of Za<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dok the prieſt, who readily performed the commandement &amp; wil of Dauid, 1. Re. 1.33.38. of Hilkian the prieſtwhich doth as Ioſiah co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded him. 2. Reg. 22. 12.14. of the Leuits &amp; prieſts which did as Iehoſhaphat charged them, 2. Chro. 19. If one were a prophet, he hath an example in Nathan, who doth humble obeyſance in the preſence of Dauid, as we ſhewed before in Ieremiah which ſpeaketh moſt humbly &amp; reuere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly to Zedekiah, calling him his Lord y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> king &amp;c. though he had put him in priſon wrongfully, Ier. 37.20. in Daniel, who honored Nebuchadnezzar, ca. 4. &amp; Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rius ca. 6.21. If one were of royal pare<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage, he hath example to honor y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> king in Mephiboſheth, who fel on his face,
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:12801:37" rendition="simple:additions"/>&amp; did reuerence before Dauid. 2. Sam. 9.6. If a man of verie great ſubſtance, he hath an example in Barzillai the Gileadite, whoſe reuerend behauiour and dealing toward the ſame Dauid is ſet forth and commended. 2. Sam. 17. &amp; 19. If a moſt politike counſeller, he hath example of his dutifulneſſe to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward the prince in Huſhai the Archite the friend of Dauid. 2. Sam. 15. If a moſt valiant captaine, he hath example gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen him in Abner. 2. Sam. 3.21. in Ioab 1. Chron. 21.3. in the three mightie men, 2. Sam. 23.16.17. The like examples we may finde in the word for all other eſtates and degrees whatſoeuer.</p>
               <p>This doctrine is cleare, yet there are which gainſay it: as the Anabaptiſts on the one ſide, the Papiſts on the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſide. The Anabaptiſts denie all magiſtracie and princely gouernment among Chriſtians, imagining it to be a matter that cannot ſtand with the nature of true chriſtianitie, for one to receiue honor as a Prince, and another to giue &amp; yeeld ſuch honour as a ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect:
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:12801:37" rendition="simple:additions"/>who are eaſily refelled. For to whom is this commandement here of honoring the Prince giuen by S. Peter? it is no giuen to chriſtian men? yes ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rely, eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to thoſe whom before he cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth liuing ſtones, an holy nation, a roi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all prieſthood, &amp;c. which are the titles of all true chriſtians. Would S. Peter haue commanded that, which was not agreeable to chriſtianitie? No verelie, we ſee then, how chriſtianitie will not bolſter out any man to diſhonour the king, no more than it will grant a man to caſt of and reiect the feare of God. For as a duetie of chriſtianitie the one is required of men; namely, to <hi>feare God,</hi> and <hi>honor the king</hi> or prince: and thus the miſt of Anabaptiſtical doctrin vaniſheth at the ſhining forth of that light, which vttereth it ſelf in this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept of S. Peter. The papiſts, they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uay their poiſon another way: for they do not ſimplie denie honor to princes, but to thoſe princes whom their <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mish antichrist</hi> diſalloweth and is diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſed withall: to ſuch they thinke
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:12801:38" rendition="simple:additions"/>themſelues, that is to ſay, all papiſts to owe no duetie, but to be lawfully quit &amp; diſcharged from their oath of allea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gance and al duetifulnes toward them by their Pope: neither that alone, but moreouer account it lawfull for them which are borne ſubiects to ſuch prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, to blaſpheme, hurt, and murther them, if by any meanes poſſible they may, as hath appeared by the ſatanical attemps of late Engliſh traitors againſt our ſoueraine. This is as eaſily co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>futed by S. Peter in this place as the former opinion was, if we conſider what man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner kings and princes had then the go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernement when ſaint Peter gaue this precept. Were kings at that time fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uourers of religion? did they further the preaching of the word, wherof pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter was a miniſter? Did they eſteeme Peter or any other the Apoſtles or faithfull children of God? No ſuch thing; but contrariwiſe they were eni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies of the goſpel, they labored by all meanes to hinder the paſſage &amp; courſe of the truth, they perſecuted Peter &amp;
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:12801:38" rendition="simple:additions"/>all the reſt of the godly; For all this, S. Peter, who was taught &amp; ſpake by the holy ghoſt, durſt not will any man to diſhonor them or to ſlay them, but (as this place declareth) he charged true chriſtians and all that feared God to <hi>Honor the king,</hi> which as many as fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red God &amp; were true chriſtians indeed accounted it their duetie inuiolably to performe &amp; do. Did Peter commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen the vngodly kings &amp; enimies of the truth to be honored of all y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> were true chriſtians? and may the blafphemous Pope by that fulnes of iniquitie &amp; de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceitfulnes, wherwithal the diuel poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth him, perſwade me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> now adays, that they may at his commandement &amp; for wrecke of his anger, blaſpheme with mouth, &amp; aſſalt with ſword the maieſty of their ſouerain prince, who laboreth by al means to bring me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of true godlines &amp; right practiſe of the ſame, &amp; yet be right catholikes, true chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, &amp; ſuch as do no more the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in duty they are bound to do? O mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrous co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trariety, declaring their Pope
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:12801:39" rendition="simple:additions"/>to be Antichriſt, in that he taketh vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him to change this law of God, Dan. 7.25. concerning the honoring of kings ſet downe by ſaint Peter, and his complices not to be true chriſtians or ſuch as feare God, but the very me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of Antichriſt &amp; ſons of perdition.</p>
               <p n="4">4 We are now come to the laſt point propounded in our former diui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion: which is, for what cauſes the king is to be honored in manner aforeſaid.</p>
               <p n="1">1 And firſt of all, a ſpeciall matter which putteth men in minde and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>acteth of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to honor the king, is, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe this vocation is the ordinance of God, againſt which to ſpurne, or to worke or ſpeak any thing which carri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth matter of diſhonor therewithall, were ſo far forth to ſpurne, worke, or ſpeake againſt God himſelfe. That the kings office and vocation is the ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of the Almighty, the ſcripture moſt plainly affirmeth. The Queene of Saba ſpeaking to Solomon, ſaith on this manner, <hi>Bleſſed</hi> (ſaith ſhe) <hi>be the Lord thy God vvhich loued thee to ſet</hi>
                  <pb n="73" facs="tcp:12801:39" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <hi>thee on his throne as king in ſteede of the Lord thy God, and hath made thee king ouer Iſraell, &amp;c.</hi> 1. Reg. 10. She ſaith that the Lorde did ſet him on the throne of the kingdome, and that the Lord his God made him king ouer Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael. Neither was this a thing peculiar and proper to Solomon onely and his kingly authority alone, but the ſame is true of other alſo. For ſaint Paul Rom. 13. generally auoucheth how <hi>all power is of God:</hi> and that in this reſpect the prince is to be honoured, ſaint Paul in the ſame place proueth, vſing this ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie argument and reaſon, <hi>Becauſe it is the ordinance of God, and whoſoeuer reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteth the povver, reſisteth the ordinance of God.</hi> Hereunto adioine the prophet Dauid, who Pſalm. 2. exhorting his e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies quietly to yeeld him the honor of his princely power and authoritie, and not to rebell and riſe ſtill againſt him, vſeth this amongſt other as a rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to perſwade them withall, becauſe he was <hi>Chriſtus Domini,</hi> the annointed of the Lord, and becauſe <hi>The Lord had</hi>
                  <pb n="74" facs="tcp:12801:40" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <hi>appointed him his king vpon his holy mou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of Sion.</hi> In co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſideration wherof, he ſaith not how they bended the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues againſt him the anointed of the Lordalone, but affirmeth how they <hi>ſtood vp against the Lord &amp; againſt his anointed,</hi> as reckning the Lords caſe &amp; the kings in this point to be al one. Mark (derly beloued) what amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtrous ſin this is, which whoſoeuer wittingly co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>miteth, walketh preſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuouſly and with a ſtiffe necke not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the ſtreame of mans power and ſtre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gth, but againſt the inuincible ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie of God himſelf. O my brethren, I beſeech you in the name of Chriſt Ieſu do not ſo wickedly, be no counſellers nor partakers with any rebellious per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons; what ſhal ye that are but dry ſtub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, yet by ſuffering your ſelues to bee carried headlong with the whirlwind of popiſh doctrine againſt our God, which is a co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſuming &amp; deuouring fire.</p>
               <p n="2">2 A ſecond matter which calleth vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> men to render this dutie of honour to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> king, is, the marke wherat he aimeth in all that he goeth about: which is, the
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:12801:40" rendition="simple:additions"/>welth &amp; good of the ſubiects. For ther unto he laboreth both by power &amp; by councell, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the inheritance of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lord committed to his charge, may floriſh, grow &amp; increſe outwardly in abu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of worldly bleſſings, inwardly in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifold graces of Gods ſpirit, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked may be ſuppreſſed &amp; feared from breking forth vnto thoſe vngodly ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, wherby looſnes may be brought in amongſt men: that alſo outward eni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies round about the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> may haue peace with thoſe that he ruleth, &amp; not annoy any warlike or hoſtil force or inuaſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s. This the Scripture and word of God a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoucheth. S. Paul Rom. 13. affirmeth concerning the wel diſpoſed, how the king or higher power is <hi>the miniſter of God to ſuch an one for his good.</hi> King Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomon Pro. 20.26. as touching the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked and hurtful perſons, ſheweth what a ſoueraigne remedie is to be found in roial power &amp; authoritie againſt the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, <hi>A wiſe king</hi> (ſaith Salomon) <hi>ſcattereth the wicked, &amp; cauſeth the wheele to turne ouer them.</hi> Neither can theſe things be
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:12801:41" rendition="simple:additions"/>performed and brought to paſſe with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out great care, trauell, coſtes, coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell, and danger on the princes behalfe, by reaſon of the rebellious affections of mans nature where withal he is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually to ſtriue both by rewards and and puniſhmentes. In conſideration whereof, for ſo great paines and bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fites to requite the prince againe, not with honour and dutifulnes, but with bloudſhed, rebellion, or conſpiracie, can not but be a ſinne vnmeaſurablie ſinnefull.</p>
               <p n="3">3 Not to ſtand much on this point, I will adioine but this one reaſon. S. Paul Rom. 13. aforenamed verſ. 2. ſaith, how <hi>They which reſiſt and rebell against the higher powers, get vnto them ſelues iudgement.</hi> And what iudgement (bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren) meaneth he? Verely the iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Gods heauie plagues and of moſt ſhamefull death to carrie them out of this world, and of vnappeaſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able vengaunce to reſt and knawe vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon them in that euerburning lake in the worlde to come. Theſe are not
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:12801:41" rendition="simple:additions"/>bugges wordes to fraye you alone, but the verie and plaine trueth which the word will furthermore teach you. As touching the ſtate of ſuch perſons in the world to come what it ſhall be, ye may take great aime hereby, conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering how it is hardly to be reade in the whole ſcripture, where the pat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternes of Gods mercie toward ſinners falling into euill are propounded, that euer God ſuffred any of his elect ones after their effectuall calling, to be car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried of the deuill into this ſinne of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion againſt the prince. Adde here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto, that ſaint Paule reckoneth this enormity among thoſe which whoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer committeth, <hi>Shall not inherit the kingdome of heauen.</hi> Tit. 1.16. Concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning their moſt fearefull puniſhments in this world, marke the moſt certaine examples of the holy worde of God. Korah, Dathan and Abiram rebelled againſt Moſes, therefore <hi>They died not the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon death of all men, but the Lord wrought a new thing, ſo that the earth o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened her mouth and ſvvallovved them</hi>
                  <pb n="78" facs="tcp:12801:42" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <hi>vp vvith all that they had, &amp; they vvent dovvne quicke into the pit.</hi> All which was done, to make vs vnderſtand, that ſuch rebels <hi>prouoke not man but God him ſelfe.</hi> Num. 16.29.30. Abſolom the goodly though vngodly ſonne of righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous Dauid, rebelled againſt his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the king, and therefore as hee rod vpon his princely mule vnder a great oake, the verie boughes of the tree would not ſuffer ſo wicked a wretch to eſcape vnpuniſhed, but caght hold on his head, <hi>And he vvas taken vp be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tvveene the heauen and the earth, there hanging till Ioab his greate friend came &amp; thruſt him through vvith three darts, beſide the vvounds vvhich ten other men the ſeruants of Ioab gaue him.</hi> Yea, ſo li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle was the face of the kings ſonne re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerenced becauſe of his treaſon, that he had none other ſepuchre but a dung hil pit in the wood, none other tombe or hearſe but a ruinous heape of great ſtones caſt vpon him, 2. Sam. 17. Sheba the ſonne of Bichri a man of Iemini re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>belled againſt the ſame Dauid: there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:12801:42" rendition="simple:additions"/>the Lorde deſtroied him by the hands of them which were his friends. For the men of Abel to whom hee fled for helpe, at the counſell of a woman cut off his head, and did caſt it ouer the wall to Ioab, 2. Sam. 19. Adde hereun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the examples of late traitors in this our owne Countrie, as <hi>Sommeruile, Throgmorton, Babington,</hi> &amp; their com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plices, which like dunghill cockes en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending to pearch vppon the head of this realme to the deſtruction thereof, were iuſtly conſtrained to crowe their laſt vppon the gallowes. The like (O Lord) we beſeech thee bring vpon all the enemies of Elizabeth thine anoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, but let peace be vpon the Iſrael of God, and vpon all that vnfainedly ſeeke her true honour in the right feare of the Almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Laus ſolt Deo.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
